<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle or exhortacion, to vnitie [and] peace, sent fro[m] the Lorde Protector, [and] others the kynges moste honorable counsaill of England: to the nobilitie, gentlemen, and commons, and al others the inhabitauntes of the realme of Scotlande</title>
            <author>Somerset, Edward Seymour, Duke of, 1506?-1552.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68723</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22268</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110952</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846399</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846399</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11362</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68723)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11362)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 133:12, 153:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle or exhortacion, to vnitie [and] peace, sent fro[m] the Lorde Protector, [and] others the kynges moste honorable counsaill of England: to the nobilitie, gentlemen, and commons, and al others the inhabitauntes of the realme of Scotlande</title>
                  <author>Somerset, Edward Seymour, Duke of, 1506?-1552.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In aedibus Richardi Graftoni, typographi Regii,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Excusum Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno salutis humanæ M.D.XLVIII. [1548]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The Lorde Protector = Edward Seymour, Duke of Somerset.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An epistle exhortatorie.</note>
                  <note>There are several title-page variants with undetermined concurrence: no comma after "exhortacion"; "fro̲" instead of "frō"; "Englan:d".</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 9181 on UMI microfilm reel 133.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery and the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 133 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy) and at reel 153 (British Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Edward VI, 1547-1553 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Mary Stuart, 1542-1567 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11362:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11362:1"/>
            <p>¶ An Epiſtle or exhortacion, to vnitie &amp; peace, ſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lorde Protector, &amp; others the kynges moſte honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble counſaill of England To the Nobilitie, Gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tlemen, and Commons, and al others the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitauntes of the Realme of Scot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lande.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:11362:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11362:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Edward, by the grace of God Duke of Somerſett, Erle of Hertforde, Viſcount Beauchamp, lorde Seimour, vncle to the kynges highnes of Englande, Gouernor of his moſte royall perſone, and Protector of all his Realmes, dominions and Subiectes, Lieuetenaunt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of all his Maieſties Armies, bothe by lande and ſea, Threaſauror and Erle Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall of Englande, Gouernor of the Iſles of Gerneſey &amp; Ierſey, and Knight of the moſte noble ordre of the Garter, with others the Counſaill of the ſaied moſte high and noble Prince <hi>EDVVARD,</hi> by the grace of God of Englande, Fraunce and Irelande, kyng, defender of the Faithe, and in yearth vnder Chriſte the ſupreme hedde of the Churche of Englande &amp; Irelande: To the nobilitie, and counſailors, gentlemen and the commons, and all others the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitauntes of the realme of Scotland: Gretyng and Peace.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>ONSIDE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng</hi> with our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſtate of thynges, &amp; wei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng more depelye the maner and termes, wherein
<pb facs="tcp:11362:3"/> we and you do ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de: It maketh vs to merueile what euil &amp; fatal chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce doth ſo diſſeuer your har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, and maketh theim ſo blinde and vnmindfull of your profite and to ſtill conciliate and heape to your ſelf mooſte extreme miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes: the whiche, we (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you will nedes haue your enemies) go aboute to take awaie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you and perpetually to eaſe you ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of. And although by all reaſone and ordre of neceſſitie, it ſhould bee rather more conuenient for you to ſeke and require, mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate agrementes of vs (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god hath hetherto, accordyng vnto our moſte iuſte, true, and Godly meanynges and inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſet forwarde, with youre affliccion and miſerie) then that we, beyng ſuperiours in the feld
<pb facs="tcp:11362:3"/> Maſters of a great part of your realme, ſhould ſeke vpon you: Yet to thintent that our charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mynde and brotherly loue, ſhould not ceaſe by all meanes poſſible, to prouoke and cal you to youre awne commoditie and profite, euen as the father to the ſonne, or thelder brother would do to the yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger brother: And as the louyng Phiſicion, would do to the miſtruſtfull and ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t pacient, we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to call and crye vpon you, to looke on your ſtate, to auoyde the greate cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie your Countrey is in: To haue vs rather brothers, then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, rather Countreymenne, then Conquerours. And if your Gouernor or Capitaines, ſhall reteigne and kepe from you this oure exhortacion, as heretofore
<pb facs="tcp:11362:4"/> thei haue doen: our Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tendyng to the like effecte, for their awne priuate wealth &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, not regardyng though you bee ſtill in miſerie, ſo they haue profite and gouernaunce ouer you, &amp; ſhall ſtill abuſe you, with feyned and forged tales: Yet this ſhalbee a witneſſe afore God, and all Chriſtian people, betwixte you and vs, that wee profeſſyng the Goſpell of Chriſt accordyng to the doctrine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, doo not ceaſe to call and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke you, from theffuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your awne blood, from the deſtruccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the realme of Scotland, from perpetuall enemitie and hatred, from the finall eradicacion of your nacion, and from ſeruitude to foreyne nacions: to libertie, to amitie, to equalitie with vs, to
<pb facs="tcp:11362:4"/> that, whiche your writers hath alwayes wiſſhed, mighte once come to paſſe. <hi>VVHO</hi> that hath<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red thiſtories of tyme paſte, and doth marke and note the greate battailes, fought betwixte En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande and Scotland, thincur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, roades, and ſpoyles, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hath been doen on bothe the parties: The realme of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande fiue tymes wonne by one kyng of Englande: The Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhe kynges, ſome taken priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſome ſlain in battaill, ſome for very ſorowe and diſcomforte vpon loſſe, diyng and departing the world: and ſhall perceiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, that of all nacions in the worlde, that nacion onely beſide England, ſpeaketh theſame lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage: and as you and wee bee annexed and ioyned in one Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande,
<pb facs="tcp:11362:5"/> ſo no people ſo like in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, forme, language, and all condicions as we are: Shal not he thynke it a thyng verie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mete, vnnaturall, and vnchriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that there ſhould be betwixte vs ſo mortall warre, who in reſpect of al other nacions, be, &amp; ſhould bee, like as twoo brethren of one Iſlande of greate Britayn? And though he were a ſtraungier to bothe, what would he thynke more mete, then if it wer poſſible one kyngdome be made in rule, whiche is one in language, and not to be diuided in rulers, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is all one in Countrey. And for ſomuche as twoo ſucceſſions ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not concurre and fal into one, by no maner of other meanes, then by mariage, whereby one bloude, one lignage and paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,
<pb facs="tcp:11362:5"/> is made of twoo, and an indefecible right geuen of bothe to one, without the deſtruccion and aboliſhing of either: If god ſhould graunt that whatſoeuer you would wiſh, ſhould be doen what could you wiſh, other then that, whiche now, not by fortune hath chaunced, but by his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercie and moſte inſcruta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prouidence, as carefull for you, he hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto you. The whiche thyng, that you ſhould alſo thinke to come of his diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicion, and not by blynd fortune how vnlikely hath it been, &amp; how ſodainly hath it turned, that the power of God might be ſhewed: Your laſt Kyng beyng a Prince of muche excellencie and young, (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you know, after a promiſe broken contrary to his honour:
<pb facs="tcp:11362:6"/> And a miſfortune by iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of GOD folowyng vpon it, GOD either by ſorowe, or by ſome other wiſe at his inſcruta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pleaſure, did take away from you) had three children. Did not almightie GOD, as it were to ſhewe his will and pleaſure to be, that the long co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued warre and ennemitie, of bothe the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhould be taken awaie, and knit in perpetuall loue and ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, take the two men children of thoſe babies, beyng diſtaunt the one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other, and in diuerſe places, bothe as it were at one tyme, and within the ſpace of xxiiii. houres, leauyng but one mayden child and Princeſſe?</p>
            <p>When the moſte wiſe and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Prince, late our Kyng and Maſter, kyng He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry theight
<pb facs="tcp:11362:6"/> in other of his mariages not moſt fortunate, had by his moſt lawful and moſte verteous wife Quene Iane, his other two wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes before that mariage depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this worlde, and neuer ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe nor queſtion made of that mariage, fithe that tyme to this daie, nor ſo muche as all her life tyme, name or mocion, to, or of any other wife, one Prince of ſo high expectacion, of ſo greate giftes of God, the right and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted heire of the Realme of England, and his maieſtie one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of male iſſue, left behynd hym to ſuccede the imperial Croune. If nothyng els had been dooen, what can any wiſe or any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian manne, that thynketh the worlde to be gouerned by Gods prouidence, and not by fortune,
<pb facs="tcp:11362:7"/> thinke otherwiſe, but that it was Gods pleaſure it ſhould bee ſo, that theſe twoo realmes ſhould ioyne in mariage, and by a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament, make a Godly, perpetuall, and moſte frendly v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and concord. wherby ſuche benefites, as of vnitie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord commeth, may through his infinite grace, come vnto theſe realmes. Or if any man of you, or of any other nacion doubteth hereof, excepte that you loke for miracles to bee doen herein, and yet if ye marke all the poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the natures of the twoo princes, the children alredy had, the doubtfull chaunce, leaſt eche of theim ſhould haue a ſonne, or bothe doughters, or not of mete ages, with other circumſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces both of the partie of this realme
<pb facs="tcp:11362:7"/> of Englande, and that of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, whiche hath not chaunced in viii. C. yeres, it muſt nedes be reconed a greate meruaill and a miracle. But let it be no miracle ſeyng that God dooth not nowe ſpeake in oracles as emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges the Iewes he did: And preſent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies now a daies, bee but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not certain, or els not plain, What more certaintie can bee had of Gods will in this caſe, then the before reherſed dooeth bryng? But if GOD hymſelf ſhould ſpeake, what could he ſpeake more then he ſpeaketh in theſe: cal you them prouidences or chaunces? If you bee ſtill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted and puniſhed, may he not ſaie: I of my infinite mercie and loue to your nacion, had proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a right heire and a prince to
<pb facs="tcp:11362:8"/> the one, and a right heire &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the other, to bee ioyned in my holy lawes, and by the lawe of nature, and the world to haue made an vnitie, concorde, and peace, in the whole Iſle of bothe the realmes, you refuſed it, you loued better diſſencion then v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, diſcorde then agremente, warre then peace, hatered then Loue and Charitie. If you doo then therfore ſmart for it, whom can you blame, but youre awne eleccion? <hi>BVT</hi> becauſe ſome of thoſe, who maketh hereto impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimentes, who cannot but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that there appereth Gods prouidence herein, and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geuen, to vnite both the realmes: yet may here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſaie, and heretofore hath ſaied, that the faulte herein is,
<pb facs="tcp:11362:8"/> that wee ſeke not equalitie, nor the mariage, but a conqueſt, wee would not be fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, but be lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Although our Proclamaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at the laſte warres, dooeth enough declare the contrary, yet here wee proteſte and declare to you, and all Chriſtian people, to be the kynges Maieſties mynd, our Maſters, by our aduiſe and counſaill, not to conquer, but to haue an amitie, not to wynne by force, but to conciliate by loue, not to ſpoyle and kil, but to ſaue and kepe, not to diſſeuer and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce, but to ioyne in mariage from high to low, bothe the real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, to make of one Iſle one realme, in loue, amitie, concorde, peace, and Charitie. Whiche if you refuſe, and driue vs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere, who is giltie of the blood
<pb facs="tcp:11362:9"/> ſhed? Who is the occaſion of the warre? Who maketh the battai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, the brennyng of houſes, and the deuaſtacion whiche ſhall fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe? <hi>CAN</hi> it be denied, but that we haue the great ſeale of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, graunted by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Scotlande, for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage whiche ſhould bee made, with aſſuraunces and pledges, vntil the performau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce? And this in the tyme that the late kyng of moſte famous memorie, our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigne Lorde kyng Henry the eight did reigne, and in the tyme of theſame your Gouernor, who now is the erle of Arreigne, who then beyng a chief dooer and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borer therein, for the high &amp; ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable benefite of that realme. So ſone as he was by the late Cardinall of <hi>S.</hi> Andrews and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb facs="tcp:11362:9"/> with certain vain feares &amp; hopes, and gredines of dignitie peruerted, reuolted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his firſt agrement, and put al the realme to the loſſe of ſuche holdes and fortreſſes, as be now taken from you: and to the loſſe of a fough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten feld, for the which we are ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, if otherwiſe peace could haue been co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded, for his awne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate lucre, &amp; recheleſnes of that noble Realme. And what ende canne you loke of this maner of procedynges, but ſuche ſucceſſe as heretofore hath been experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted and aſſaied: we offre loue, we offer equalitie &amp; amitie, we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome in war, and offer peace, wee wynne holdes, and offre no conqueſt, we gette in your lande and offre Englande: What can be more offered and more profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb facs="tcp:11362:10"/> then entercourſe of merchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diſes, enterchaunge of mariages the abholiſhyng of all ſuche our lawes, as prohibiteth theſame, or might bee impediment to the mutuall amitie. We haue offerd not onely to leaue thaucthoritie, name, title, right, or chalenge of conquerours: but to receiue that whiche is the ſhame of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed, to leaue the name of the nacion, and the glory of any vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie if any wee haue had, or ſhould haue of you, and to take the indifferent old name of Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes again, becauſe nothyng ſhould be left, of our part vnof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, nothyng of your part vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refuſed, whereby you might bee inexcuſable: And all the worlde might teſtifie, all other meanes not beyng able to do any thyng,
<pb facs="tcp:11362:10"/> after many other waies and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted: Battaill of vs to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as an extreme refuge, to atteigne righte and reaſon, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monges Chriſtian men. <hi>IF</hi> any man maie rightfully make bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taill, for his eſpouſe and wife: the daughter of Scotland, was by the greate ſeale of Scotland, promiſed to the ſonne and heire of Englande. If it bee lawfull by Gods Lawe, to fighte in a good querell, and for to make peace: This is to make an ende of all warres, to conclude an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and perpetuall peace, whiche to confirme, wee ſhall fighte, and you to breake, is it not eaſie to decerne who hath the better parte? <hi>GOD</hi> and the ſworde, hath all ready, and ſhall hereafter, if there bee no remedie
<pb facs="tcp:11362:11"/> trie it. Who ſo willeth the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to goo forwarde, who myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the peace and tranquilitie of bothe the Realmes, who wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth no conqueſt to bee had, but amitie and loue to bee eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed betwixte vs, wee refuſe no manne: let hym bryng his name and his pledge, of good ſeruice in this querell, he ſhal not onely be receiued to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> amitie, but ſhal haue ſufficient defence agaynſte the aduerſaries: <hi>VVE</hi> neither do nor intend, to put any man from his takkes or offices, onleſſe he will needes reſiſt, &amp; ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pell vs thereunto. what face hath this of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queſt? We intend not to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſherit your Quene, but to make her heires, inheritors alſo to En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gland. What greater honor can you ſeke vnto your Quene, then
<pb facs="tcp:11362:11"/> the mariage offred? What more meter mariage then this, with the kynges highnes of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d? What more ſure defence, in the noneage of your Quene, for the Realme of Scotlande, then to haue England patron and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon? We ſeke not to take from you youre lawes nor cuſtomes: But we ſeke to redreſſe your op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, whiche of diuerſe, you do ſuſtein. <hi>IN</hi> the realme of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, diuerſe lawes and cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes be, accordyng to the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent vſage of the parties thereof. And likewiſe in Fraunce, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy, and Gaſcoigne, hath ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dery kynd of ordres: Hath al the realmes and dominions whiche the Emperor now hath, one and one ſorte of lawes? Theſe vain feares and phantaſies, of expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb facs="tcp:11362:12"/> of youre nacion, of chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng the lawes, of makyng a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>queſt, bee driuen into your hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, of thoſe who in deede, had rather you were all conquered, ſpoyled, &amp; ſlain, then thei would loſe any poynte of their will, of their deſire of rule, of their exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimacion, whiche thei knowe in quietnes would bee ſene what it wer, as it were in a calme water. Now in this tumulte of diſcord whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the realme is toſſed vp and doune, with waues and ſourges of battaill, famyne, &amp; other miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, whiche the warr bringeth, thei thynke thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be eſpied. But looke on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, you that haue wit and prudence, and conſider the ſtate of your Quene and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme: <hi>YOV</hi> wil not kepe her ſole and vnmaried, the whiche were
<pb facs="tcp:11362:12"/> to you greate diſhonour. If you mary her within the realme, that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not extynguiſh the title which we haue to the Croune of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande: and what diſſencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, enuie, grudge, and malice, that ſhall brede emonges you, it is eaſy to perceiue. You will mary her out of the Realme: our title remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, you be ſubiectes to a forein Prince of other Countrey, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther language: and vs ye haue youre enemies, euen at your el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowe, your ſuccours farre of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you. And be we not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bowels now of the realme? Haue we not a greate parte thereof either in ſubieccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or in amitie and loue? Who ſhall come into your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, but he ſhalbee mette with, and fought with, if nede be, euen of youre awne nacion, who bee
<pb facs="tcp:11362:13"/> faithefull &amp; true to the realme of England, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way of this moſte Godly vnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by mariage. And if any forein power, Prince or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tate, whoſoeuer be your aider, to noriſhe ſtill diſcord, ſende you an armie alſo: how ſhall thei op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe you, fill your houſes, waſt your groundes, ſpende and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume your vitaill, holde you in ſubieccion, and regarde you as ſlaues, which without the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could not liue, take your Quene to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe as thei liſt, and leaue your realme, eſpecially if their Kyng or ruler (as perchaunce he maye be) in other warres, be otherwiſe occupied, to be a pray to vs &amp; a true conqueſt. Then it ſhalbe to late to ſaie, we will haue a mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and no conqueſt, wee wiſhe peace and amitie, we are wery of
<pb facs="tcp:11362:13"/> battaill and miſerie. The ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne ouercomed muſt ſuffre the victours pleaſure, and pertina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie will make the victory more inſolent, whereof you your ſelfe haue geuen the cauſe. If thei ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d money and Capitaines, but no ſouldiors: Firſt if thei be Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, who ruleth &amp; who dooth obeye, who ſhall haue the honor of the enterpriſe, if it bee well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieued? But whether it bee well achieued or no, whiche numbre is that, that ſhalbee ſlain, whoſe bloodde ſhalbe ſhed? Their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney peraduenture ſhalbe conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and their commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes obeyed: But whoſe bodies ſhall ſmarte for it? Whoſe la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des ſhalbee waſted? Whoſe houſes burned? What realme made de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate? Remembre what it is to
<pb facs="tcp:11362:14"/> haue a forein power within you a ſtrong power of your enemies vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, you as it were the ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe and plain, betwixt them to fight on, and to be troden vpon, bothe of the victor and the ouercomed. And imagine you ſe before your iyes, your wifes and daughters in daungier of the wantonneſſe and inſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of the ſouldiours, the proude lookes of the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and ſouldiours, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you cal to helpe you, the conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt you ſhall bryng your nacion in: And then take hede leſt in deede that follow, whiche you feare, that is that you ſhalbe by them conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that you ſhalbe by them put from your holdes, la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, tackes, and offices: that youre lawes by them ſhalbe altered: That your nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe by them deſtroyed.
<pb facs="tcp:11362:14"/> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider in this realme: Did not the Britaynes call in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xons for helpe, and by theim wer put out? Where bee the Pictes, once a great nacion betwixt you and vs? Howe did the nacion of Fraunce put out the Galles out of all Fraunce? Howe gotte the Turke firſt all Grecia, and now a late Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>garie, but beyng called in for to aide and helpe? And did not the Gothes by like meanes get all Italie? And the Lombar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des one part thereof, now called Lombardy? What loke you for more? Nedy ſouldiours and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng the weapons in their han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, &amp; knowing that you cannot liue without them, what wil thei not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde you to do? What wil thei not encroche vpon you? What will thei not thynke thei
<pb facs="tcp:11362:15"/> maie dooe? And what will thei thinke that you dare doo? This forein helpe is your confuſion, that ſuccour is your detriment, the victory ſo had, is your ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, what is then to be thought of loſſe taken with theim? The ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers and forein ſouldiours ſhall oppreſſe you within, oure power &amp; ſtrength without: And of youre awne nacion, ſo many as loueth quietnes, Godlines, and the wealth of your realme, ſhall helpe alſo to ſcourge and afflicte you. Is it not better to compoſe &amp; acquiete al this cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie and trouble by mariage? To ende al ſorowes and battai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, by ſuche and ſo honorable a peace? How hath the Emperour Spayne and Burgondy, not by title of mariage? Howe holdeth
<pb facs="tcp:11362:15"/> the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che king Briteigne, now lately adnexed to that Croune, not by title of mariage? Howe hath al the greate princes of the worlde happely, and with quiete made of two kyngdomes one, of diuerſe lordſhippes one? of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions alwaies at warre with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf, or els in doubtful peace, one well gouerned Kyngdome, rule and dominion, but by that moſt Godly, moſte quiete, moſte ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable compoſicion of mariage? Two meanes ther is of makyng one rule, whereto title is preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and perfite agreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t betwixt twoo nacions: Either by force &amp; ſuperioritie whiche is conqueſt, or by equalitie and loue, whiche is parentage and marryng: ye hate the one, that is conqueſt, and by refuſyng the other, you
<pb facs="tcp:11362:16"/> enforce it vpon you: you wil not haue peace, you will not haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaunce, you will not haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde: and conqueſt commeth v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon you whether you will or no: And yet if all thynges were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, wee feare it will appere, that it were better for you to bee conquered of vs, then ſuccoured of ſtraungiers, leſſe loſſe to your gooddes, leſſe hurte to youre lande, leſſe diſhonor to your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme: This nacion which is one in tongue, one in Countrey and birthe, hauyng ſo litle diuerſitie to occupie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers to come into you, neither like in language, ne yet like in behauior, who ſhould rule ouer you, and take you to be but their ſlaues. But we efteſones and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally declare, and proteſt vnto
<pb facs="tcp:11362:16"/> you, that although for the better furtheraunce of this godly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, of vniting the realmes, and for the ſure defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of theim, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che fauoreth the mariage, we are compelled for the tyme, to kepe holdes, to make fortificacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in youre Realme: Yet the Kynges Maieſties mynde, and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate pleaſure, with oure aduiſe and counſaill, to bee as before is declared, where fauour maie be ſhewed, not to vſe rigoure, if by condicions you will receiue this amitie offered, not to followe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, we deſire loue, vnitie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, peace and equalitie: let nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your Gouernour, nor your Kirkmen, nor thoſe who ſo often hath falſefied their faithe &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and by treacherie and falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed, be accuſtomed to prolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the
<pb facs="tcp:11362:17"/> tyme, fede you further with faire wordes, and bryng you into the ſnare, from whence thei cannoe deliuer you. Thei wil peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture prouide for themſelues, with pencions in ſome other Realme, and ſett ſouldiours ſtraungiers in youre holdes, to kepe you in ſubieccion, vnder pretenſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende them againſt vs. But who prouideth pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cions for you? How are you defended, when thei bee fled awaie? Who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quereth you whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtraunge ſouldiours or Capitaines hath your holdes? When your land is waſted, and the realme deſtroyed, &amp; the more part kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you? Who will ſet by the mariage of the Quene, to buye a title with the war of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande, to mary the name, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mightie Kyng holdyng the
<pb facs="tcp:11362:17"/> lande? If we twoo beyng made one by amitie, bee moſte hable to defende vs againſt all nacions: and hauyng the ſea for wall, the mutuall loue for garriſon, and God for defence, ſhould make ſo noble and wel agreyng Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, that neither in peace wee maie bee aſhamed, nor in warre affraied, of any worldely or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein power: why ſhould not you bee as deſirous of the ſame, and haue as muche cauſe to reioyſe at it as we? If this honour of ſo noble a monarchie, do not moue you to take and accepte amitie, let the grief and the daungier of the before named loſſes, feare you to attempt that thyng whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſhall diſpleaſe God, encreaſe warre, daungier youre Realme, deſtroy your landes, vndo your
<pb facs="tcp:11362:18"/> children, waſte your groundes, deſolatey oure Countreis, and bryng all Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de either to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myne and miſerie, or to ſubieccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſeruitude of another nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wee require but your promiſed Quene, your offred agrement of vntiie, the ioynyng of bothe the nacitons: whiche God of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite clemencie and tendre loue that he hath declared, to beare to bothe the nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, hath offered vnto vs bothe, and in maner cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs bothe vnto it: <hi>VVHOSE</hi> callyng &amp; prouocacion, we haue and will followe, to the beſte of oure powers, and in his name, and with his ayde, admonicion, exhortacion, requeſtes, and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſaides, not beyng hable to do it, and to finde ſtablenes in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes: We ſhal not willyng, but
<pb facs="tcp:11362:18"/> conſtreined, purſue the battaill chaſtice the wicked and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, by the angrie Angelles of GOD, the Fire and Sworde. Wherefore, wee require &amp; exhort all you, who hath loue to youre Countrey, pitie of that realme, a true hart to your quene &amp; Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, regarde of youre honors and promiſes, made by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greate Seale of Scotlande: And who fauoreth the peace, loue, vnitie, and concord, and that moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable mariage, to entre and to come to vs, and declaryng your true and godly hartes therunto, to ayde vs in this moſte Godly purpoſe &amp; enterpriſe: be witneſſe of our doynges, we refuſe no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> temporall ne ſpirituall, lorde ne larde, gentilman, ne other, who will ayde this our purpoſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:11362:19"/> miniſhe the occaſion of ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and deſtruccion, to whom we ſhall kepe the promiſſes hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore declared, and further ſee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward &amp; recompence made accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to deſerte. And for a more ſure profe, and playner token of the good mynd &amp; wil whiche we beare vnto you: that whiche ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yet before was graunted to Scotlande, in any league, truce or peace, betwixt Englande and Scotlande, becauſe you ſhall haue profe of the beginnyng, of loue and amitie of bothe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>almes: the kynges highnes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideryng the multitude of them, whiche is come to his maieſties deuocion, and of theim that bee well willers and ayders, of this Godly enterpriſe, hath by oure aduiſe and counſail graunted, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:11362:19"/> by theſe preſentes doeth graunt, that from hencefurthe, all maner of merchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, and other Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhmen, who will entre their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, with one of the lieuetenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes or wardens of the Marchies or any other of the Kynges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties officers hauyng auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and there profeſſe to take parte with vs, in this before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med godly purpoſe, to his awne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie, and to ſerue all ſuche as be of theſame agrement: may lawfully, and without any trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vexacion, entre into any Porte, Creeke, or Hauen of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande, and vſe their trafique of merchaundiſe, either by lande or ſea, bye and ſell, bryng in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie of Scotlande, and take and cary furth the commodities of England, as liberally and as
<pb facs="tcp:11362:20"/> frely, &amp; with theſame, &amp; no other cuſtome or paimentes therefore, then Engliſhmen, &amp; the Kynges ſubiectes doth at theſe preſentes myndyng further vpon the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe hereof, to gratifie ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers of this moſte Godly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe and vnion, that all the world may be witnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great zeale and loue, whiche his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes dooeth beare, towardes you and your nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And all this the Kynges highnes by our aduiſe and counſaill, hath willed to bee declared vnto you, and geuen in commaundement to vs, and all his Lieuetenauntes, Wardens, Rulers, and other hed officers, miniſters &amp; ſubiectes, to ſee exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted and doen, according to the true purporte, effecte and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng therof. Fare you well.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11362:20"/>
            <p>At Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the v. of Februarij in the ſeconde yere of the reigne of the moſte noble Prince and our ſouereigne Lorde, Edward the <hi>.VI.</hi> by the grace of God of Englande, Fraunce &amp; Ireland, kyng, defender of the faith, and in yearthe vnder Chriſt the ſupreme hedde of the Churche of Englande and Irelande.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:11362:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>EXCVSVM</hi> LONDINI, IN AEDIBVS RI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHARDI GRAF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TONI, TYPOGRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PHI REGII.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno ſalutis humanae. M.D.XLVIII.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CVM PRIVILEGIO AD IMPRIMEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DVM SOLVM</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11362:21"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
